A Guide to the Tracy W. McGregor Autograph Collection, ca. 1599-1947
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
- SERIES I. LETTERS & MANUSCRIPTS
  - Royal Patent granted to Bernardo de Galvez by Charles III of Spain, containing an official account of his achievement in Louisiana during the struggle between Spain and Great Britain for domination in the Southeastern region of present day United States. 1783 May 20, AD, 35p. (Box 4)
    Galvez fought against the Apaches in 1763 on the Eastern border of New Spain, and in 1776 he returned to America as a Colonel and Deputy Governor of Spanish Louisiana, distinguishing himself by his handling of border incidents with Great Britain along the Mississippi. In 1779, on the outbreak of war with Great Britain, he was promoted to Brigadier-General and Governor, capturing Fort Manchak, Baton Rouge, and Mobile by 1780. In 1781, his conquest of Pensacola earned him his second title of Viscount Galvez; #6163
  - Horatio Gates, Orders and Instructions, for Colonel Semp, to survey the coasts and posts on Southside Virginia in expectation of the French fleet; and if the fleet of the enemy shall appear, to immediately report to Governor Thomas Jefferson on their numbers, strength and probable destination; with a list of officers appointed by Congress 1780 Oct 14, ADS & AD (Box 4)
  - [Charles?] Townshend, by the command of King George II, to Lord Mayor of London, James Bateman 1716 Dec 7, ALS, 1p. (Box 4)
    Writes concerning taking up a collection for the poor of London and asks Bateman to assist the Bishop of London with the collection; #10547-x
  - Minutes in French of the Privy Council of Great Britain's reply to the Spanish memorial concerning General James Oglethorpe, the Governor of Georgia, who was in Great Britain organizing the defense of the colony. The Spanish demanded that neither Oglethorpe nor any fresh troops be allowed to go to Georgia. ca. 1737, AD, 3p. on 1 l. (Box 4)
    This document is a contemporary copy of the British reply in which the King maintains all his rights to Georgia and other territories claimed by Spain; #9407
  - United States Military Telegraph, Manassas, Colonel Alfred Gibbs to Colonel C. Ross Smith 1863 Oct 13, telegraph (Box 4)
    Reports on Major [Rufus] Scott's return from a scouting expedition to Thoroughfare Gap; both Scott and Gibbs were in the 19th New York Cavalry; #495
  - George Robert Gissing to Algernon Gissing 1881-1886, 9 ALS (Box 4)
    Gissing mentions the return of his wife, Nell, his lack of leisure to spend in writing a second book, and the dangers of procrastination (1881); congratulates his brother on the completion of his examination, his wife determined to return to Soho Square to live, is busy writing his last will and testament, and reading about Italy (1882 May); Helen's arm to be operated upon, asks about an edition of Byron without Don Juan, and plans to send his paper on pessimism (1882 Nov 5); his wife has gone to live in [Brinton ?], taking half of their furniture, hopes to have another novel finished by midsummer, and he pays Nell a pound weekly (1882 Dec 27); advocates learning to read German, recommending Goethe by Lewes, and the essays by Thomas Carlyle about Goethe, and his purchase of engravings by Raphael (1884 Sep 18); gas explosion on the ground floor of his building, Jean Ganssen now staying with him, discusses Buchanan's In Stormy Waters, "It puzzles me how a man capable of fairly good work can condescend to the most amazing trash in this way," and says that the third volume of his novel advances (1885 Feb 28); praises George Meredith's Diana of the Crossways as Shakespeare in modern English (1885 Apr 29); recasting his novel [ Isabel Clarendon] into two volumes, enjoying the Reminiscences of Crabb Robinson, and is spending about eight hours a day writing (1885 Aug 5); has a check for Letty Coe from Bentley, and is worried about Algernon's silence (1886 Dec 23); #10547-h
  - Report of the Good Will Home Association, Hinckley, Maine 1932 Jun 7, TMs, 18p. (Box 4)
    #10547-aw
  - Alfred Thomas Scrope Goodrick to "My dear Huten" 1908 Nov 11, ALS, 4p. (Box 4)
    Congratulates recipient on his college appointment and disputes historical accuracy in Sydenham Poyntz's book on Spain; #10547-ax
  - Receipt signed by Daniel Gookin and related material, including a letter about Gookin genealogy and heraldry, and three clippings of reviews about the book Daniel Gookin 1808, 1874, 1913, ADS (Box 4)
    #10547-ay
  - Harry Gordon, Senior Engineer, to Mr. Thornton 1764-1765, 2 ALS (Box 4)
    Writes concerning affairs between the British and the Indians, mentions troubles with Indians near Detroit and Fort Michilimackinac, difficulties with building fortifications in the area, and French success with the Indians (1764); he also writes about finishing his reports on the inland forts with a map of their locations, the few numbers of British troops in his area, the poor condition of the forts, partially due to the nature of the materials used in their construction and repair, the management of troops, and the plan to survey the area around the south shore of Lake Erie (1765); #10547-az
  - F.D. Grant to W.S. Wells, enclosing an autograph signature of Ulysses S. Grant 1886 Jun 10, ANS, withenvelope (Box 4)
    #10547-ba
  - William Grayson to John Kercheval, including a letter from Spence Grayson 1786, 7 ALS (Box 4)
    Grayson, first Senator from Virginia, writes to Kercheval concerning the management of his land, his affairs, and the closing of the grist mill, while he is away serving in the Congress in New York; #1106-c
  - Financial & Legal Papers of the William Grayson Family, including promissory notes, receipts, bills, and bonds 1771-1790, 12 items (Box 4)
    #1106-c
  - Report of the Committee of the Parliament of Great Britain concerning the London fire of 1666, including several unrelated fragments ca. 1666, AMs, 4p. (Box 4)
    #10547-bb
  - George Washington Greene to Abram S. Eastlake 1873 Apr 12, ALS, 4p., with envelope (Box 4)
    Writes concerning the papers of General Mad Anthony Wayne; #10547-bc
  - A Summons issued by Samuel Green, a Massachusetts printer, to Edward Rawson, Captain Thomas Clark & Captain Richard Davenport 1653 Jul 29, ADS, 1p. (Box 4)
    Concerning land in Middlesex County, Massachusetts, and involving the Glover and Winthrop families; #10547-j
  - Angelica & Sarah Grimke to Mrs. Smith, including a cut autograph signature of Angelina Grimke [ca. 1838], 2 ALS (Box 4)
    The letters are about their attempt to get some letters and a package containing Sarah's Letters on the Equality of the Sexes to their mother in Charleston, South Carolina, by Peter Parker, since at the time the postal authorities in Charleston were opening and destroying all letters from the Grimke sisters except those by personal conveyance; #2824
  - Earl of Halifax to Robert Dinwiddie concerning the frontier defense of Virginia 1754 Jul 6, ALS, 8p. (Box 4)
    In which he gives advice on the conduct of the current conflict with France over lands around the Ohio, reprimands the Lt. Governor for not acting sooner, assures him of British support and hopes he will soon retake a fallen fort and two French ones recently built on English territory. He urges cooperation with South Carolina governor James Glen and the bribing of the Cherokee Indians; #2963
  - Letters from Thomas Hardy to "Dear Sir," Gerald Maxwell, and Charlotte Mary Maw 1882-1919, 3 ALS (Box 4)
    Hardy comments that he has nothing for magazine publication at the present (1882); speaks favorably on the Court Journal, but has nothing for the Christmas issue as he is busy with the second part of The Dynasts(1905); and thanks Maw for her poem included in a volume for him by his poet friends; #10547-bd
  - Joel Chandler Harris to Richard Watson Gilder n.y. Apr 26, ALS, 2p. (Box 4)
    Discusses the form of Where's Duncan and explains what he understood about the agent of Routledges and the pirating of Free Joe and other Georgian sketches; #10547-be
  - Manuscript note concerning an unknown English actress, formerly believed to be in the hand of William Hazlitt n.d., AMs (Box 4)
    #10547-bf
  - Patrick Henry to Edmund Pendleton 1776 Oct 21, ALS (Box 4)
    Writes that Fielding Lewis, who was elected a councilor by the Assembly, has sent word by George Thornton that he is utterly unable to serve in that capacity due to illness; #4918
  - Patrick Henry to Henry Lee 1794 Feb 1, ALS, 2p. (Box 4)
    Discusses Colonel George Hairston and his uncanny ability to collect revenue for the public treasury though taxes; #6868
  - Patrick Henry to John Tabb 1784 May 22, ALS, 2p. (Box 4)
    Writes concerning the purchase of some land Tabb has advertised and proposes some terms; #6089
  - Joseph Hiller to Edward Watts 1709/10 Feb 1, ALS (Box 4)
    Discusses his deeds he has not received, sends Watts money collected from rents and comments on his difficulties in obtaining silver currency; and says that Increase and Cotton Mather and other Boston representatives have petitioned the court concerning Governor Richard Bellingham's will; #10547-bg
  - William J. Hobby to Seaborn Jones 1793 May 22, Typescript copy (Box 4)
    Discusses the financial and legal situation concerning a bond he gave to Jones; #10547-bh
  - Poems by Oliver Wendell Holmes, including an excerpt from "A Voice of the Loyal North" and "Union and Liberty" 1861 & 1881, 2 AMsS (Box 4)
    #10547-bi
  - "The Mather Literature" a listing of the holdings of the library of William Gwinn Mather, compiled by Thomas J. Holmes 1926, TMs, 42p. (Box 4)
    #10547-bj
  - Holston Treaty with the Cherokee Nation 1791 Jul 2 (Box 4)
    The treaty, concluded at French Broad [Knoxville, Tenn.] sets the boundary line between the United States and the Cherokee Nation, guarantees to the Nation all land outside the boundary line and cedes to the U.S. all land within the line. The U.S. pays "certain valuable goods" and $1000 annually to the Cherokees for their land and the Cherokees agree to be under the protection of the U.S. and no other nation. The U.S. reserves the right to regulate trade and navigation of the Tennessee River. Crimes by either party will be punished by U.S. law, retaliation is to end, animosities cease and prisoners restored. The U.S. will also supply interpreters and free farming implements; #10858
  - A.E. Housman to Charles Wilson 1933 & 1935, 2 ALS (Box 4)
    Mentions Wilson's political activities and comments on an illness; #10547-k
  - Laurence Housman to Charles Wilson 1929 Mar 22, ALS (Box 4)
    Writes Wilson regarding his plans to read A.E. Housman's poetry on the radio, to edit War Letters for Victor Gollancz Ltd. And to publish Cornered Poets: A Book of Dramatic Dialogues; #10547-k
  - Letters from William Henry Hudson, with a photograph of his winter home at Penzance [1905]-1920, 5 ALS (Box 4)
    Describes a goshawk, discusses extrasensory perception, and his health, mentions his work and sets a luncheon date; #10547-l
  - Unpublished Manuscript concerning the early life of William Henry Hudson, and a letter from Edward Garnett about the manuscript 1935 Mar 7, AMs, 2p. (Box 4)
    #10547-l
  - Leigh Hunt to Thomas Richards 1813 Jul 15, ALS, 2p. (Box 4)
    Sends regrets that illness prevents Richards from coming to see him and hopes to arrange another time; #10547-bl
  - Complaint by Joseph Hyde accusing Silas Harrison of violating Sabbath laws in Connecticut 1777 May 27, ADS (Box 4)
    #10547-bn
  - Charles J. Ingersoll to Mrs. Dolley Madison 1836 Sep 2, ALS (Box 4)
    Offers his opinion that she will be unable to collect on the debt owed her by John Stockton Littell, who has a good character but not much money; and offers his assistance in publishing James Madison's works; #10547-bo
  - Andrew Jackson to Mrs. Rachel Jackson 1818 Jun 2, ALS, 2p. (Box 4)
    Writes of his successful prosecution of the Indian War against the Indians of northern Florida at St. Marks and Pensacola and his plans to march to Columbia, [South Carolina?]; #1648
  - Memoirs of a Monticello Slave, the Reminiscences of Isaac Jefferson about life of Monticello recorded by Charles Campbell ca. 1847, AMs, 22p. (Box 4)
    #2041
  - List of Names found with the Thomas Jefferson Poplar Forest Papers, some associated with University of Virginia [ca. 1826?], AD (Box 4)
  - Edward Jenner to Charles Beckford Long 1801 Aug 17, ALS, 3p. (Box 4)
    Sends vaccine virus and explains the inoculation procedure; #10547-bp
  - John Keats to Thomas Richards 1818 Oct 9, ALS (Box 4)
    Says he is unable to visit because of the illness of his brother; #10547-bq
  - Legal Brief: Walter King vs Carter Braxton 1753 Jun 6, 17 pages (Box 4)
    Concerning land in Albemarle County, Virginia; #4441
  - Harry Lauder to "Dear Miss Markell," with caricature of Harry Lauder by himself 1924 Feb 11, ALS (Box 5)
    Comments that her song, although good, is not for him; #10547-bs
  - Handwritten copies of the public papers of Henry Laurens [1778-1790], AD, 83p. (Box 5)
    #2298
  - Papers of Thomas Law (1759-1834) 1803-1834, 45 ALS, 4AMs (Box 5)
    Law came to America in 1794, when 35 years old and had distinguished himself in India. He settled in Washington City, prospered and married Elizabeth Parke Custis, a grand daughter of Martha Washington. He came in contact with most of the prominent men of his time, including presidents. Thus the letters contain much information about the growth of the United States and the capitol, politics, the War of 1812, anti-Jackson sentiment, trips to springs in Virginia, a visit to the University of Virginia, the death of Judge Selden in a duel, affairs in India, and much personal news. Many of these letters are addressed to his sister, Joanna, who married Sir Thomas Rumbold, a prominent East India Company official; #2801
  - Thomas Edward Lawrence to David McAdam Eccles 1924 Dec 5, 25, 2 ALS (Box 5)
    Writing as T.E. Shaw, discusses Eccles' subscription to Seven Pillars of Wisdom, the price and expected number of copies, the typeface used, and warns that the book may be dull; #10547-bt
  - Portrait and Printed Biographical Sketch of Tobias Lear (1762- 1816), private secretary to George Washington n.d. (Box 5)
    #10547-bu
  - Arthur Lee to Captain Cleveland 1777 Apr 6, ALS (Box 5)
    Writing from Paris, Lee informs him that Mr. Merckle has assured the arrival of goods from Amsterdam worth about 10,000 pounds, which will be awaiting the Captain at Bordeaux and wishes him a prosperous voyage; #2281
  - Arthur Lee to [C.W.F. Dumas] 1778 Nov 12, ALS, 4p. (Box 5)
    Writes to see if Dumas thought it possible for Lee to obtain a loan from Holland for one million sterling for the United States; #2281
  - Arthur Lee to John Hopkins 1788 Mar 20, ALS (Box 5)
    Requests that Hopkins send him newspapers from time to time concerning the election of members to the [Constitutional?] Convention placed within sealed letters, so the post office will still deliver them; #5589
  - Richard Bland Lee to David Stuart 1789 & 1794, 2 ALS (Box 5)
    Discusses the proceedings of Congress concerning the preparation of a customhouse system, compensations to be made to the President, Vice President and members of the Legislature, an import bill, the judiciary system, the fifth article of the Constitution, and the health of President Washington (1789) and also defends his character to his constituents, mentions the peace concluded with the Six Nations, diplomacy with Great Britain, and the domestic agitations in France(1794); #4385
  - Richard Bland Lee Letters to Zaccheus Collins, Thomas Jones, Theodorick Lee, James Madison, his wife, Elizabeth Collins Lee and son, Z. Collins Lee 1790-1826, 13 ALS (Box 5)
    Mentions bill in favor of the Potomac (1790); the possible tour of James Madison through the Eastern states, the excise tax, bank bill, and the selection of the site for a federal city [Washington City] (1791); the death of Mr. Lewis and his concern to secure someone else to care for his plantation affairs, and the death of his mother [Lucy Grymes Lee] (1792); the conduct of Mr. Genet, and the proceedings of the Indian commissioners (1793); lease agreement (1795); request to Madison for a civil government position (1812); request for an appointment to the position of commissioner of claims for property destroyed during the War of 1812 (1816 Apr-May); description of Kentucky (1820); offers advice to his son attending the University of Virginia (1826); #3684
  - "Notes to an Original Federalist of the Old School," apparently a draft of an address by Richard Bland Lee on the nation's fiftieth anniversary [1826], AMs, 8p. (Box 5)
    #3684
  - Richard Henry Lee to Arthur Lee 1779 Aug 12, ALS (Box 5)
    Writes concerning Hezekiah Ford, Arthur Lee's secretary, and his safe arrival with all the dispatches for himself and Congress, the arrival of the new minister Chevalier de la Luzerne from France, the recall of Silas Deane, and James Lovell, Chairman of the Committee of Foreign Correspondence in the Continental Congress; #2523
  - Andrew Lewis to George Washington 1770 Mar 1, ALS, 2p. (Box 5)
    Concerning land claims of former soldiers along the Monongahela River, with a note on the verso in George Washington's hand "Col. Andr[ew] Lewis 1st Mar. 1770 Upon my obtaining an order of survey"; #3620
  - Flora Virginia Milner Livingston to Mr. Wells and Mr. Gomme 1926-1935, 7 TLS (Box 5)
    Concerning Rudyard Kipling bibliography; #10547-bv
  - Letters from the Bishops of London and Winchester 1742-1750, 3 ALS (Box 5)
    Concerning collections for aid to the poor of London; #10547-bw
  - Count de Revilla Gigedo, Mexico City, to Don Diego de Gardogin 1793 Apr 30, ALS (Box 5)
    About establishing trade relations between provinces of Louisiana and Texas; #10547-bx
  - James Russell Lowell Letters to W.J. Robinson, James Bradstreet Greenough, Frank Harrison Hill, and Mary Louise Boyle 1849-1887, 5 ALS (Box 5)
    Lowell writes regarding a lecture spot for Charles V. Kraitsir in the Lowell Lyceum, the North American Review's treatment of the Hungarian movement, Bibles in the King's Library (Spain), Ticknor Catalogue proofs, "A new edition of the dictionary," an incorrect London Daily News story on army troops in Cincinnati, the treatment of criminals in the United States, letters of Walter Savage Landor, and Hallam Tennyson's "Jack the giant killer." A.H. Clough is mentioned; #10547-m
  - Lord Thomas Babington Macaulay to "Sir" 1848 Jan 1, ALS, 2p. (Box 5)
    Declines an invitation to preside over an evening event; #10547-by
  - Letters from Dolley Madison 1804-1840, n.d., 19 ALS, with typed transcripts (Box 5)
    Dolley writes chiefly to her sister, Anna Payne Cutts, and cousins, Mrs. Van Zandt and Mrs. L. Henry Cutts, but also to Richard Smith and Mrs. Thornton, primarily concerning family matters, but also: wigs (n.y. Aug 2); difficulties in reaching Montpelier because of bad roads and swollen rivers (n.y. May 13); a letter from Thomas Jefferson about the death of Maria and the deep grief of the family (1804 Apr 26); and the delicate health of James Madison ([1805] Jul 29).
    Dolley also writes concerning problems with her knee and her memory of the Society of Friends, "our Society used to control me entirely and debar me from so many advantages and pleasures, and tho so entirely from their clutches, I really felt my ancient terror of them revive to disagreeable degree." ([1805] Aug 19); Madison going to the office though ill with a cold; Thomas Jefferson has a sick headache every day; Colonel Aaron Burr on the way to Richmond for trial ([1807] Mar 27); marriage of sister Lucy Payne Washington and Supreme Court Judge Thomas Todd of Kentucky; Federalists refuse to enter the Madison's doors ([1812] Mar 20); disappointed in her desire to see Payne at Montpelier; and the affairs of her brother-in-law John George Jackson (1830 Jan 25).
    Other topics include: gift of a scarf; the inflammation of her eyes (1838 Oct 8); intense concern for her sister's health (n.y. May 18); trouble with her knee keeping the family from returning to Orange; regrets not being able to nurse her through this childbirth; anxious to place Payne at Baltimore in the fall (n.y. Jul 8); urges her sister to visit and sends money for Payne to come home (Friday); Madison confined to bed though in constant receipt of visitors and mail; receipt of the curls and silk from Mr. Ballard; Payne gone to the gold mine (n.d.); suffering from inflammatory rheumatism (n.y. Jun 3); #1661
  - James Madison and Theodorick Bland to Governor Benjamin Harrison 1782 May 14, ALS, 6p. (Box 5)
    Discusses the proposed cession of Virginia's western land claims to the national government; the Revolutionary War; the French alliance; and the Virginia-Maryland boundary dispute; #2019
  - James Madison Letters to "Dear Sir," Thomas Morris, and Fulwar Skipwith 1803-1814, 3 ALS (Box 5)
    Mostly discusses the claims of American citizens against foreign countries (1803 Nov; 1804 Nov 10; & 1814 [post Jun 27]); #2474
  - James Madison to Tench Coxe 1804 May 8, ALS, 1p. (Box 5)
    Requests Coxe to forward 75 copies of the laws of the United States intended for Louisiana to Governor Claiborne at New Orleans, and 25 to Governor Harrison at Ft. Vincennes, for distribution to the Louisiana territory; #1595
  - James Madison to Richard Cutts 1817 Oct 12, ALS, 2p. (Box 5)
    Discusses keeping Mr. Bizet, [the gardener?] on at Montpelier as better suited than a stranger; asks him to check the post office at Washington and see if they have his missing issues of the Weekly Register and to retrieve for him his personal copy of a history about Benedict Arnold's treason from [Richard] Rush who may have thought it belonged to the Department of State; #2288
  - James Madison to Richard Cutts, Joseph Delaplaine, and C.D. Cleveland 1818-1827, 4 ALS (Box 5)
    Plans to leave soon for Rockfish Gap and is looking forward to a visit from Mrs. Cutts (1818 Jul 27); comments about the package of Talavera wheat sent by Cutts' agency (1818 Nov 25); asks Delaplaine to send him the manuscript papers containing memoranda relating to himself because there might be inaccuracies and two pamphlets, one on the British doctrine of neutral trade and "Political Observations" and thanks him for the volume of poetry by Mr. Mead (1820 Oct); as rector of the University of Virginia, thanks C.D. Cleveland for the copy of Epitome of Grecian Antiquities which he will add to the University Library (1826 Apr 28); #1661
  - James Madison to Joseph C. Cabell 1818, 1830, 3 ALS (Box 5)
    Discusses his lack of enthusiasm for the offer of a position as a member of the Board of Public Works; the opposition of William and Mary to the establishment of Central College, and their inability to obtain Dr. Thomas Cooper for Central College (1818 Feb 23); the loss of law professor John Tayloe Lomax from the University of Virginia, Madison's bouts of influenza, mismanagement of his rural affairs, and his loan of a pamphlet by Mr. Grimke to Cabell (1830 Apr 10); discusses possible candidates to replace Professor Lomax at the University of Virginia; "the nullifying doctrine" of South Carolina and the use made of the Proceedings of Virginia in 1798-1799 (1830 Sep 12); #4645
  - James Madison to Benjamin Silliman 1820 May 25, ALS, 1p. (Box 5)
    Sends the cost of his subscription to the scientific journal published by Professor Benjamin Silliman; #2803
  - James Madison to Martin Van Buren 1826 Apr 28, ALS, 1p. (Box 5)
    Discusses Van Buren's observations on the modifications of the federal court system to accommodate a rapidly expanding America; #4888
  - James Madison to James Monroe 1828 Feb 5, ALS, 1p. (Box 5)